Finding Aid for University of Michigan Center for Chinese Studies Records 1958-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Center for Chinese Studies (University of Michigan) Records
1958-2010
1963-1982
University of Michigan. Center for Chinese Studies.
A cross-disciplinary center for the study of Chinese history, culture and contemporary Chines society at the University of Michigan, includes administrative records of the Center and information on research, lecture series, exhibits and other activities of the center.
89511 Bimu C26 2
9 linear feet
296 MB
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
These records were transferred by the Center for Chinese Studies in February 1989 (Donor No. 7658 ); additional materials were transferred in 1997.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open for research.
The Center for Chinese Studies (CCS) was formed in 1961, and grew from an "area studies" tradition that was pioneered at the University of Michigan. Area studies are cross-disciplinary in nature to encourage broad and integrated understanding of various cultures. The area studies tradition at the university started in 1936 with the development of the Oriental Civilizations Program, which included instructors from eight different departments who were all specialists on Asia. The Center for Japanese Studies was formed in 1947 and has served as the model adopted by the Center for Chinese Studies as well as other area studies programs around the nation. At the University of Michigan the two centers have always enjoyed a close working relationship and jointly share many administrative tasks. Interest and financial support for area studies programs increased in the late 1950s with the passage of the National Defense Education Act and the Ford Foundation's decision to commit substantial funds for training and research in the field of Chinese studies. Initial funding for the CCS came from a ten year-Ford Foundation grant which was supplemented by a National Defense Education Act East Asia Center grant.
Over the years the CCS has gained national recognition due to the efforts of its first two directors, Albert Feuerwerker and Alexander Eckstein. Both men served on a variety of national, professional and governmental committees relating to the study of and interaction with the People's Republic of China. The papers of Eckstein and Feuerwerker are housed at the Bentley Historical Library and are a source of additional materials for the researcher. A complete list of directors of the CCS since its inception is found on page iii.
The center serves a variety of roles and is responsible for coordinating most activities on the University of Michigan campus relating to China. Pertinent departmental classes are coordinated by the CCS which also administers several interdisciplinary classes. The undergraduate and master's degree programs in Asian Studies, the Asia Library, and the Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE) are administered by CCS in conjunction with other area centers. PASE is a pioneer university outreach effort designed to improve the quality of study of East Asia in small midwestern colleges and secondary schools, as well as to educate the American public on the societies, traditions and problems of East Asia.
The CCS encourages research on China by awarding research funds to both Michigan faculty and to scholars from around the world who come to Ann Arbor to conduct their research. Research findings are often published by the CCS in Michigan Papers in Chinese Studies, a quarterly journal, or in a monograph series, which was formerly published by the University of California Press but is now "issued by" the University of Michigan Press.
The center provides a variety of services to its students. It administers a graduate fellowship program to help offset the financial burdens experienced by graduate students who pursue an advanced degree in an area studies program. Fellowships are awarded to assist promising students to study in Asia. Since the interdisciplinary nature of the program results in a certain amount of faculty decentralization, the center serves as an important meeting ground for students and faculty. This role is supported primarily through the 'brown bag' lunches and colloquia programs.
Directors of the Center for Chinese Studies
1961-1962 Albert Feuerwerker
1962-1963 Alexander Eckstein, acting director
1963-1967 Albert Feuerwerker
1967-1969 Alexander Eckstein
1969-1972 Rhoads Murphey
1972-1975 Albert Feuerwerker
1975-1976 Rhoads Murphey, acting director
1976-1980 Albert Feuerwerker
1980-1981 Allen Whiting, acting director
1982-1983 Albert Feuerwerker
1983-1985 R.F. Dernberger
1985-1989 Kenneth Lieberthal
2003-2008 Jams Z. Lee
2008- Mary Gallagher
The Center for Chinese Studies record group consists primarily of material for the years 1962 to 1994. Overall strengths of the collection include documentation of PASE, records of the Asia Library (1962-1982), and course information from curriculum development (1960s). Yearly budget and financial records are fairly complete, except for the period from 1971 to 1976. The gap is unfortunate because it was during these years that the Ford Foundation grants ended and the center had to search for new funding sources. Other material is broadly illustrative of the diversity of the tasks undertaken by the center.
The record group, as received by the Bentley Library, mostly consisted of loose documents and random topical folders. It now consists of topical folders arranged alphabetically within five series. The series Directors Correspondence and the Asia Library are in their original order, as received by the library; Administrative Records, Activities, and Printed Materials are artificial groupings created to provide order and easy access to the records.
The Bentley Historical Library received another large transfer of records from the Center for Chinese Studies in 1997. Spanning the years 1966 through 1994, these consist primarily of administrative files and information pertaining to the activities which the Center for Chinese Studies organized or in which it participated. The records were relatively well organized when it was attained by the Bentley Library. The original order of the records was retained with the exception of some files pertaining to the East Asian Capital Campaign. These were reorganized so that they could be located in one series.
Subjects:
China--History--1949-; China--Study and teaching.; University of Michigan. Asia Library.; University of Michigan--Research.
Subjects - Visual Material:
China--History--1949-1976.; Exhibitions.; Medicine--China.
Contributors:
Feuerwerker, Albert.; Murphey, Rhoads, 1919-; Whiting, Allen Suess, 1926-
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Administrative Records, 1962-1991
  - 1962-1982
    The Administrative Records (1.5 linear feet) series contains materials relating to the daily operations of the CCS, the various projects it administers, and its interaction with the other area centers. They include correspondence, minutes, financial records, syllabi, reports, and proposals. Documents pertaining to the early history of the center, including several from 1958 which document the initial proposals to create the unit, are present in this series as are the fairly comprehensive PASE records. Class materials pertaining to the development of an interdisciplinary curriculum can be found in the Course files. The Correspondence files relate mostly to administrative tasks and intradepartmental communication. There are substantive reports concerning the state of the center in 1974 in the Faculty Retreat folder. The Executive Committee and Faculty Meetings folders contain correspondence but only scattered minutes.
    - Affirmative Action, 1971-1980 (Box 1)
    - American Council of Learned Societies, 1969; 1975-1977 (Box 1)
    - Area Centers, 1962-1969 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Area Studies Committee, 1959-1965 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Bibliography (of publications by center faculty and associates), 1972; 1977 (Box 1)
    - Budget, 1961-1982
      - CCS
        - 1961-1970 (Box 1)
        - 1977-1982 (Box 1)
      - Chinese Economic Studies, 1962; 1964-1967 (Box 1)
      - East Asian Economic Systems, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
      - National Science Foundation Grant, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
    - Chinese Materials and Research Aids Service Center, Inc., 1967-1968 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1981
      - Office, 1969; 1971-1979; 1981; 8 folders (Box 1)
      - Eckstein, Alexander, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
      - Feuerwerker, Albert, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts Administration, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
      - Miscellaneous, 1962-1966 (Box 1)
    - Courses, 1958-1978
      - General Files, 1962-1978 (scattered) (Box 1)
      - Correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 1)
      - Enrollment, 1958-1977 (Box 1)
      - Syllabi, undated, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
      - Syllabi, 1969 (Box 1)
    - East Asian Capital Campaign (see also box 3), 1977-1980 (Box 1)
    - Economic Studies Proposal, 1974-1975 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee, 1977-1981 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Meetings, 1975; 1979 (Box 1)
    - Faculty Retreat, 1974 (Box 1)
    - Far Eastern Languages and Literatures, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - Far Eastern Studies-MA and BA Programs, 1967-1969 (Box 1)
    - History of Asian Studies, 1958 (Box 1)
    - History Department, 1968 (Box 1)
    - International Studies Building, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
    - Lane Hall, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Project on Asian Studies in Education (PASE), 1971-1979 (Box 2)
      - General Files, 1971-1979; 4 folders (Box 2)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities Grant Applications, 1972-1973 (Box 2)
      - Proposal-"The US and Southeast Asia: Reflections on the Past and Prospects for the Future,", 1976 (Box 2)
      - Report of Task Force PASE, 1971 (Box 2)
      - Report to the Michigan Council for the Arts, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Project on East Asian Studies in Education (PEASE),., 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Proposal for the Michigan Center for Research and Training in Arms Control and Weapons Management, undated (Box 2)
    - Proposals for Research on Contemporary China, 1965-1966 (Box 2)
    - Publication Guidelines, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Publication Policy, 1966-1971 (Box 2)
    - Research Associates, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
    - Research Guides to Red Guard Publications Project, 1974-1977 (Box 2)
    - Research Proposal to the International Communications Agency, 1979 (Box 2)
    - Summer Faculty Training Seminars, 1964 (Box 2)
    - University of California Press, 1965-1973 (Box 2)
  - 1966-1991
    The Administrative subseries series, 1966-1991, (4.5 linear feet) encompasses materials pertaining to the day to day operations of the Center for Chinese Studies. This includes budgetary information, correspondence, and grant reports/proposals. Of this series, the NDEA Proposals and Reports subseries is especially rich. It contains information relating to research conducted at the center, course offerings, degrees awarded, fellowships, publications, and activities. The Executive Committee Minutes subseries gives an overview of the Center for Chinese Studies from 1975 to 1991.
    - Alumni Questionnaire, 1975 (Box 5)
    - Area Centers-External Reviews
      - Asian Studies, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Report to LSA Dean, 1981 (Box 5)
    - Area Studies
      - Non-Western Course Requirement Proposal, 1980 (Box 5)
      - Area Studies Committee, 1980-1983 (Box 5)
      - Asia Library, 1982-1983 (Box 5)
      - Asian Studies Committee, 1972-1983 (Box 5)
      - Asian Studies Program--Graduate and Undergraduate, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
    - Board Report, 1977 (Box 5)
    - Budget, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
    - Calendar of Events, 1990-1991 (Box 5)
    - Center for International Business Education, 1990 (Box 5)
    - Chang Ching-Kuo Foundation, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Chronology
      - Contracts, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Executive Committee, 1983 (Box 5)
    - Committee to Examine Area Centers, 1972-1974; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Correspondence
      - Budget, 1975-1982 (Box 5)
      - D. H. Chen Foundation, 1977-1984 (Box 5)
      - Chairmen and Directors, 1981-1982 (Box 5)
      - General, 1979-1981 (Box 5)
      - Internal Memos, 1983 (Box 5)
      - Literature, Science, and the Arts, 1973-1983 (Box 5)
    - Director/Associate Director Appointments, 1978-1981 (Box 5)
    - East Asia Business Program, 1985-1989; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - East Asian Capital Campaign
      - Alexander Eckstein Memorial Fund, 1977 (Box 5)
      - Board of Visitors, 1976-1978 (Box 5)
      - Board of Visitors Meeting, 1976 (Box 5)
      - Board of Visitors Meeting, 1977 (Box 5)
      - Corporate Prospects, 1976 (Box 5)
      - DOW Chemical Company, 1977-1983 (Box 5)
      - Ford Motor Company, 1979-1983 (Box 5)
      - Foundations, 1977-1984; 5 folders (Box 5)
      - Fundraising Brochure, 1976 (Box 5)
      - General Motors, 1978-1980 (Box 5)
      - Honorary Degree Nominations, 1976-1979 (Box 5)
      - Investments, 1977-1978 (Box 5)
      - NEH Correspondence, 1977-1983; 3 folders (Box 5)
      - NEH Designating Letters, 1982-1984; 2 folders (Box 5)
      - NEH Regulations (Box 5)
      - NEH Reports, 1982-1984; 4 folders (Box 5)
      - Peking American School Gift, 1977-1984 (Box 5)
      - Steering Committee, 1975 (Box 5)
      - Steering Committee, 1977 (Box 5)
      - Steering Committee, 1978 (Box 5)
      - Taiwan, 1980; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Executive Committee Minutes, 1975-1991; 17 folders (Box 6)
    - Ford Foundation
      - Annual Reports, 1963-1975; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - General, 1974-1977 (Box 6)
      - Proposals, 1961 (Box 6)
      - Review, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Fund Raising
      - AMC, 1984 (Box 6)
      - Area Center's Development, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
      - Capital Funds Campaign, 1978-1980 (Box 6)
      - Dreams of Avarice, 1984 (Box 6)
      - East Asian Initiatives, 1988 (Box 6)
      - General, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
      - Taiwan Trip, 1987-1989; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Taylor Scholarship, 1986-1988 (Box 6)
    - Grants
      - Michigan China Project, 1987-1989; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - History
      - Activities, 1984-1985 (Box 6)
      - Ars Orientalis Correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box 6)
      - Correspondence, 1988-1990 (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous, 1981 (Box 6)
      - Owens Corning, 1994 (Box 6)
      - Spring Autumn Papers, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
      - Summer Teachers Institute, 1985-1988 (Box 6)
      - Visitors, 1987-1995 (Box 6)
    - Inglis House Retreat, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
    - Institute for Public Policy Studies, 1977 (Box 6)
    - International Studies, 1979-1980; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Journalism Program with Area Studies, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Luce Foundation
      - Carter Administration China Policy, 1981 (Box 6)
      - Closed Accounts, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Competition, 1987-1990; 3 folders (Box 6)
      - Post-Doctoral Scholars, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
      - PRC Scholars Exchange Program, 1982-1983 (Box 6)
      - Proposals, 1988 (Box 6)
      - Visiting Scholars Program, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Council for the Humanities, 1984 (Box 7)
    - Michigan Society of Fellows, 1976-1981 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous, 1975-1976 (Box 7)
    - NDEA Proposals and Reports, 1966-1983; 40 folders (Box 7)
    - NDEA Proposals and Reports (cont.), 1966-1983 (Box 8)
    - NEH Proposals, 1990-1994 (Box 8)
    - PICAS, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
    - Press Releases, 1980-1983 (Box 8)
    - Program Evaluations, 1971-1976; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Publications
      - Ars Orientalis, 1981-1983 (Box 8)
      - East Asian Science and Technology Series, 1979-1983 (Box 8)
      - Stock Report, 1983 (Box 8)
      - Correspondence, 1976-1981; 4 folders (Box 8)
    - Report for LSA History, 1976 (Box 8)
    - Research (general), 1969-1985
      - Budget Reports, 1983 (Box 8)
      - Research Commitments, 1983-1984 (Box 8)
      - Project Budget Requests, 1981-1983; 3 folders (Box 8)
      - Faculty Research Support, 1972-1977; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Faculty Summer Research, 1969-1972; 4 folders (Box 8)
      - Faculty Travel Funding, 1982-1985; 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Research (specific), 1980-1990 (Box 9)
      - Bellagio Conference, 1984-1985 (Box 9)
      - Chinese Economic Studies Program, 1981-1983 (Box 9)
      - Chinese Energy Bureaucracy, 1982-1985 (Box 9)
      - Committee on Chinese Demography (Box 9)
      - Computer Assisted Instruction, 1983-1986; 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Division of Research Development and Administration, 1982 (Box 9)
      - Charles O. Hucker, 1981 (Box 9)
      - Kenneth Lieberthal, 1990 (Box 9)
      - Shuen-Fu Lin, 1980-1981 (Box 9)
      - Jing-Heng Ma, 1984-1985 (Box 9)
      - Management of State Owned Enterprises in China, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Michel Oksenberg/James Tong, 1983-1985 (Box 9)
      - Sichuan, 1984 (Box 9)
      - Sichuan-Research Guide and Selected Bibliography, 1982 (Box 9)
      - Sichuan Seminar, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Sichuan University Trip, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Harold Stevenson, 1984 (Box 9)
      - Timothy Wixted, 1984 (Box 9)
    - UM China Task Force, 1980 (Box 9)
    - UM China Coordination Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 9)
    - University Fellowships for Minority Students, 1975-1984 (Box 9)
    - U.S./China Exchange Programs
      - CIC-PRC Exchange, 1979 (Box 9)
      - U.S.-China Education Clearing House, 1979 (Box 9)
      - Other University/China Exchange Programs (Box 9)
- Activities, 1963-1994; 2010
  - 1963-1983 (Box 2)
    The Activities series (.75 linear feet) contains materials dating from 1963 to 1982, which document various events coordinated or sponsored by the CCS. This series illustrates the diversity of CCS functions undertaken in its role as a focus for the exchange of ideas between students, faculty, scholars, and the public. The Chinese Academy of Social Sciences' (CASS) records document the Ann Arbor portion of the first visit to the United States by scholars from the People's Republic of China. Included are background materials and correspondence pertaining to the goals of the exchange and the careers of the Chinese participants. The files on China After Mao and the National Press Institute on China record efforts to educate the American public about the People's Republic of China. Included are correspondence, memos, reports, publicity, and background materials. The Chinese Medical Exhibit folder relates to a university exhibit on traditional Chinese medical practices and contains twelve photographic prints of exhibit displays. Unfortunately there is no program or description present in the collection to explain the displays in detail.
    - Ambassador Chai Zemin Visit, 1980 (Box 2)
    - Art Exchange Exhibition, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Bag Lunch and Colloquia, 1974-1978; 1981 (Box 2)
    - CCS 20th Anniversary, 1981 (Box 2)
    - Chiao-T'ung University Delegation, 1978 (Box 2)
    - China After Mao
      - Journalist Conference, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
      - Rapporteurs Notes, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Television Series, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Academy of Social Sciences (CASS)
      - Visit, 1979; 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - Delegates Background, 1978-1979 (Box 2)
      - Visit, 1981; 1980-1981 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Archivists Visit, 1982 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Economic Studies Regional Seminar, 1975-1977 (Box 2)
    - Chinese Medical Exhibit (Photographs), 1967 (Box 2)
    - Committee on International Cooperation-Far Eastern Language Institution, 1963-1965; 1967-1968 (Box 2)
    - Committee Membership Lists, 1975-1981 (scattered) (Box 2)
    - Communist China: The Year in Review, 1968 (Box 2)
    - Conference-Sino-Tibetan Language, 1971-1972 (Box 2)
    - East Asian Art History Newsletter, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Foreign Policy Seminars, 1968-1969 (Box 2)
    - Foreign Policy Workshops, 1976-1977 (Box 2)
    - Inner Mongolia Photo Exhibit, 1978 (Box 2)
    - Michigan China Council, 1977-1978 (Box 2)
    - Midwest Conference on Asian Affairs, 1978-1982 (Box 2)
    - National Press Institute on China (Box 3)
      - General File, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Drafts from Tapes of Discussions, 1968 (Box 3)
    - Ping Pong Team (1 document in Chinese), 1972 (Box 3)
    - PRC Delegation, 1974 (Box 3)
    - PRC Delegation, 1977 (Box 3)
    - Public Health in China-Conference, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - Public Health in China-Seminars, 1974 (Box 3)
    - Reception for Chinese Scholars Studying at UM, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Regents' Delegation, 1976 (Box 3)
    - Report to Hisahiko Okazaki on Chinese Studies, 1973 (Box 3)
    - State Department-China Advisory Panel, 1967-1968 (Box 3)
    - Symposium on Wen Cheng Ming, 1976 (Box 3)
    - 27th International Congress of Orientalists, 1967 (Box 3)
    - Visiting Chinese Delegations, 1979 (Box 3)
  - 1969-1994, 2010
    The Activities, 1969-1994 (.5 linear feet) subseries contains documents relating to the events which CCS organized or sponsored. It covers the period from 1969 to 1994. The Brown Bag Lunch subseries and the Alexander Eckstein Memorial Lecture subseries offer insight into topics of interest at CCS. Information pertaining to scholars active in the field of Chinese studies and research being performed at the University of Michigan and other Chinese studies programs can be found here. The Shanghai Municipal Archives Symposium subseries contains audio recordings of participants from a 2010 symposium sponsored by the Bentley Historical Library and the U-M Center for Chinese Studies in conjunction with the Sixth Joint Seminar on Archival Methods co-organized by the Bentley Library and the State Archives Administration of China. The one-day symposium on Archival Advances and Historical Research: Shanghai Municipal Archives and Beyond was held on October 28, 2010 at Palmer Commons on the U-M campus. Presentations by representatives of the Shanghai Municipal Archives were followed by commentaries from U-M faculty, Bentley Library archivists, the city archivist of Copenhagen, Denmark, and China scholars from the University of Toronto and Dickinson College. A total of thirty-six archivists from throughout China attended the event.
    - Advanced Research Seminar on China (Box 9)
    - Alexander Eckstein Memorial Lecture Series, 1983-1992
      - Dwight Perkins, 1983 (Box 9)
      - Shigeru Ishikawa, 1985 (Box 9)
      - Nicholas Lardy, 1987 (Box 9)
      - Lucien Pye, 1986 (Box 9)
      - Liu Guogang., 1987 (Box 9)
      - Liu Binyan, 1988 (Box 9)
      - Jonathan Spence, 1989 (Box 9)
      - Allen Whiting, 1991 (Box 9)
      - Saburo Okita, 1992 (Box 9)
    - Archival Advances and Historical Research: Shanghai Municipal Archives and Beyond" Symposium, 2010
      (BHL deposit ID: 89511_0001)
      - Part 1: Introduction; "New Digital Developments in Shanghai Municipal Archives" (Chang Yan)
      - Part 2: Commentary on "New Digital Developments in Shanghai Municipal Archives" (Par Cassell)
      - Part 3: "Conceptualizing Copenhagen through its City Archives" (Kristian Bak)
      - Part 4: Commentaries and Discussion (Elizabeth Yael and Nancy Bartlett); "Opening Up Archives and Development of Research on Shanghai History" (Yongjun Guo)
      - Part 5: "Interdisciplinary Approaches to Archival Research" (Wang Zheng and Wu Yicheng)
    - Brown Bag Lunch Series (Box 9)
      - 1979-1993, 9 folders (Box 9)
      - Information on Speakers (Box 9)
      - Instructions (Box 9)
    - Current Events Workshop, 1979-1981 (Box 9)
    - Governor's Commission on China, 1984-1987; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Han Exhibition, 1987 (Box 9)
    - Midwest Conference on Asian Affairs, 1982 (Box 9)
    - Woodcock Seminar, 1994; 5 folders (Box 9)
    - Vietnam, 1969 (Box 9)
- Directors Correspondence, 1972-1982